# 樱花虾油饭 节节高升
Sakura Shrimp Fried Rice
Cheering up every day
# 大爷好 二伯好
Greetings to Da Ye! Greetings to Er Bai!
# 兄弟们好 给你们拜个年
Greetings to you guys! My greetings for the New Year!
# 祝你们新年快乐
Wish you a happy new year,
# 龙虎精神 天天体力好壮
# （台湾食神 何京宝 三叔徒弟）
and wonder spirit and health every day!
(He Jingbao aka "Taiwanese God of Food", disciple of San Shu)
# 身体健康最重要
Being healthy is the most important thing
# 大家都一样好
Wish everyone to be perfectly well
# 大家都一样
Same to everyone
# - 都听懂了吗？
# - 木问题了
- Did you guys understand?
- No problemo!
# 我是他的翻译
I'm his interpreter
# 我今天做一个台湾的樱花虾油饭
Today, I'll cook a Taiwanese dish, fried rice with sakura shrimps
# 樱花虾油饭
Sakura Shrimp Fried Rice
# 我听明白了
I got it
# 二伯听明白了吗？
Did you get it, Er Bai?
# 樱花虾是台湾的特产
Sakura shrimps are a specialty in Taiwan
# 这个名字报完了 樱花虾
Now we got the name. Sakura shrimps
# 油饭
Fried rice
# 咱们不浪费时间 我先烧热水
Let's get to the point. I'll boil some water
# - 我给你切
# - 把香菇切一切
- I'll help you chop it
- Chop the shiitake mushrooms
# - 切什么样子的
# - 切丁
- Chop into what?
- Dices
# 多大的丁？
How big?
# 都可以
Whatever
# 干活不凑活啊
You take your work very seriously, huh?
# 刚才我们香菇都泡过水
We have soaked the mushrooms in water
# 经过四十分钟
for 40 minutes
# 可以放心 是熟的
Rest assured. They are cooked
# 小宝做电视节目 在咱们这里做了很久
Xiao-Bao has been making TV shows here for a long time
# - 没错
# - 东南亚也做了很多
- Yeah
- And also in Southeast Asia
# - 达人
# - 我在台湾做的比较多了
- A pro!
- I've done a lot in Taiwan
# 但是我最爱我的祖国
But I love my country the best
# 我爱北京
I love Beijing
# 北京很好
Beijing is very good
# 他马上就要到北京来了
He's moving to Beijing soon
# 北京欢迎你
Beijing welcomes you!
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 大爷二伯欢迎吗？
Do Da Ye and Er Bo welcome him?
# 欢迎
Welcome!
# 我的全名叫何京宝
My full name is He Jingbao
# 言可何 北京的京 宝贝的宝
"He", spelled "H E", "Jing" for Beijing, "Bao" for treaures
# 你看我就有北京的京了
See, I have Beijing in my name
# 北京是我家
Beijing is my home
# 在台湾有一个绰号 台湾食神
He has a nickname in Taiwan, the "Taiwanese God of Food"
# 你们就吹吧
You guys can keep bragging
# 何京宝
He Jingbao
# - 樱花虾油饭
# - 油饭
- Sakura shrimps fried rice
- Fried rice
# 就是广东的糯米饭
It's sticky rice from Guangdong
# 广东鸡饭
Guangdong chicken rice
# 你这个炒饭放醋吗？
Do you add vinegar into the fried rice?
# 有
Yes
# 真有
Yes for sure?
# 可以有
Yes if you like
# 但可以不搁
Or no if you don't
# 我们现在的油饭是一坨坨的
Now the fried rice is in chunks
# 这米饭是提前蒸好的啊
The rice has been steamed in advance
# 对 蒸好的
Yeah, steamed
# 过会教你们怎么蒸
I'll teach you how to steam later
# 先把它放进水里面
Put it in water first
# 他说一会教你们怎么蒸
He says he'll teach you how to steam later
# 对
Yeah
# 这个是什么米啊
What kind of rice is it?
# 这个是长糯米
This is long grain sticky rice
# 糯米 长糯米 长的
Sticky rice, long sticky rice, it's long
# 长粒糯米
Long grain sticky rice
# 大爷曾经做过刺猬丸子
Da Ye has made some hedgehog-like meatballs before
# 就是那个米
That's the same rice
# 长粒糯米
Long grain sticky rice
# 长糯米 我们把它推开
Long sticky rice. Let's push it out
# 因为我们这个米昨天已经泡了六个小时
As the rice has been soaked for 6 hours yesterday
# 放在上面用布蒸四十分钟
and steamed over a cloth for 40 minutes
# 所以米饭是熟的
So the rice is already cooked
# 米饭是熟的
The rice is already cooked
# 台湾人都非常喜欢吃樱花虾油饭
Taiwanese all love Sakura Shimp Fried Rice
# 因为他们过年过节都一定有
as they can't miss it in any festival
# 水开了 我们把它倒过来
The water is boiling. Let's pour it here
# 好
Alright
# 好 先滴滴水
Alright, let it drain
# 小宝 这个饭要做多久啊
Xiao Bao, how long is it going to take?
# 这个饭做得最久的是糯米
The most time consuming part is the sticky rice
# 糯米刚刚做好
The sticky rice is just prepared
# 有一份放入冰冻库
It can be left in a freezer
# 放了三个月都没有关系
and stay there for 3 months
# 要吃 过热水就好了
If you want to eat, just boil it in hot water
# 现场操作 需要多长时间？
How long does it take to prepare on site?
# 再来十分钟吧
10 more minutes I guess
# - 十分钟啊？
# - 对 很快
- 10 minutes?
- Yeah, it's fast
# 现在掐表 好
Let's start a timer. Yeah!
# - 大爷给你限时间了
# - 没问题
- Da Ye has set a time limit for you
- No problem!
# 我们要拿些香油
We need some sesame oil
# 肥油 猪肉
Pork
# 猪肉放下去
Put the pork in
# 猪肉啊
Pork?
# 对 猪肉给一下
Yeah, stir fry the pork
# 我们把那个红葱头
Now the shallots
# 干葱啊
Shallots?
# 南方的
Southern ones
# 爆出肉香
Fry the aroma out
# 炒出金黄色
Fry the golden color out
# 对对对
Yeah yeah yeah
# 很快的 OK
It's very fast. OK
# 把瘦肉再下去
Put in the lean meat
# 这个还有芋头
And also taro
# 对 芋头
Yes, taro
# 芋头切好了啊
The taro is chopped already
# 槟榔芋头
Small taro
# 我们芋头要蒸熟
The taro must be well steamed
# 对 我们把芋头蒸熟
Yeah, we must steam the taro
# 我们先炒好
We stir fry it
# 炒香了嘛 我们放在油饭上面
Now it's aromatic, we pour it over the rice
# 我们再放香油
Then add sesame oil again
# 二次 又一次放香油
The second time. Sesame oil again
# 二伯 一会吃这个
Er Bai, you can just eat this later
# 猪头你就别吃了
Don't think about the pork head
# 好 我们把樱花虾放进去
Alright, let's put in the sakura shrimps
# 樱花虾放进去了
Sakura shrimps in
# 把它炒香
Stir fry until aromatic
# 樱花虾的颜色非常绚丽
What a vividness of the sakura shrimps
# 是台湾的特产
It's a Taiwanese specialty
# 去你们那超市就有了
You can buy it from supermarkets
# 把它爆香
Make it aromatic
# 这个饭很香
It smells so good
# 放虾米
Dried shrimps
# - 虾米
# - 开阳
- Dried shrimps
- "Kai Yang" (another common name)
# 香菇
Shiitake mushrooms
# 我们把它炒香
Let's bring the fragrance out
# 这一看就是老手啊
See, this is a what a pro is supposed to look like
# 不管什么环境下 都能炒
He can cook in any situation
# 不管什么情况下 都能吹
He can also brag under any condition
# 好 都下来了
Alright. Dump everything in
# 这锅小了 少来米
The wok is too small. Don't add too much rice
# 少来点 太多了
Not too much. It's too much
# 蚝油
Oyster sauce
# 放蚝油
Put in the oyster sauce
# 蚝油
Oyster sauce
# 三大匙
Three big spoonsfuls
# 三汤匙
Three spoonfuls
# 对
Yeah
# 我们再放点老抽
Let's also add some dark soy sauce
# 老抽我们是用它的颜色
We use dark soy saue for its color
# 对
Yeah
# 再来放点 鲜味露
And also some, "Xian Lu" seasoning
# 对 来放点鲜味露
Yeah. Some "Xian Lu"
# 美极鲜
"Mei Ji Xian" (brand)
# 美极鲜有两个牌子
There are two "Mei Ji Xian" brands
# 炒我们这些
To cook these things
# 我们把它拌平均就好了
We just need to toss it in average
# 就是拌匀了
You mean, toss it evenly
# 拌平均就好了
"Toss in it average"
# 我觉得颜色有点浅
I think the color is a bit too light
# 给不给点 要不再给点老抽
Do we need some more dark soy sauce?
# 没有 金黄色比较好
No. The golden yellow color is perfect
# 金黄色比较好
The golden yellow color is perfect
# 过年过节金黄金黄
Wish everyone a golden yellow (harvest) for all festivals
# 先把它炒香
Bring out the fragrance
# 好 起锅前
Alright. Before finishing
# 放点酒
Add some cooking wine
# 出香味
for the aroma
# 我要它的香气 不是它的酒味
We take its aroma, not the alcoholic smell
# 如果在家庭里面做不容易粘锅
If you cook it at home, it doesn't stick to the wok
# 如果你一直开火就很容易粘锅
If you keep the heat on, it's easy to stick
# 很容易扒锅
It's easy to "Ba Guo"
# 他们叫粘锅
They call it "sticking"
# 过年的时候你煮好
You can cook it on the New Year's Day
# 放在铁碗里面 再放在里面
Leave it in a metal bowl
# 先放凉 包保鲜膜
Cool it down. Seal it with plastic wrap
# 要吃的时候 放进蒸炉
When you want to eat, put it in a steamer
# 拿出来倒扣
Then dump it out
# 就搞定了
Then it's done
# 好 饭做好了嘛
Alright. The rice is done
# 樱花虾
Sakura shrimps
# 哇 金玉满堂
Wow, gold and jade all over it
# 哇 还有好多樱花虾
Wow, so many sakura shrimps
# 闪亮 闪亮登场
Shiny! A shiny appearance!
# 来
Come on
# 我们放点小香菜在旁边
Let's put some cilantro by the side
# 没有樱花虾 用虾皮虾米也可以
If you don't have sakura shrimps, you can just use dried shrimp or dried Acetes
# 用小虾米
Those small dried shrimps
# 虾米跟海老什么的
"Xia Mi", "Hai Lao" or alike
# 对 海老
Yeah, "Hai Lao"
# 海老 也叫开阳
"Hai Lao", also called "Kai Yang"
# 大爷叫开阳 我们叫海米
Da Ye calls it "Kai Yang". We only call it "Hai Mi"
# 今天就简单完成了
Now it's briefly done
# - 好 真棒 漂亮
# - 谢谢
- Nice! Wonderful! So beautiful!
- Thank you!
# 有菜了 有饭了
We got the dishes! We got the rice!
# 有菜了 有凉菜了 有热菜了
We got the dishes. Cold dishes, and hot dishes
# 饭来了
Rice coming
# 年夜饭来了
The New Year's Meal is coming
# 上菜上菜
Let's serve the dishes
# 上饭
Serve the rice!
# 上饭上饭
Serve the rice, serve the rice!
# 可以吃饭了 吃饱了
We can have the rice now!
# 二伯 评价一下
Er Bai, please leave a comment
# 你看 先闻
Smell it first
# 是不是不够咸
Is it salty enough?
# 我们台湾口味比较淡
as we prefer a milder taste in Taiwan
# 刚刚好
It's just about right
Just about right
# 二伯用广东话说 “刚刚好”
Er Bai should say in Cantonese, "Gong Gong Hou"
# 你知道为什么
Do you know why?
# 因为我放樱花虾放多一些
As I put some more sakura shrimps in it
# 它的咸香味就跑下去
so the salty flavor has mixed in
# 他这个饭好就好在哪儿呢
You know, what's the best of this rice?
# 海峡两岸一家亲
Across the strait, we are a family
# 但是呢
However
# 台湾的美食非常诱人
Taiwanese food is very attractive
# 他用糯米炒
He made it with sticky rice
# 糯米的这种软糯
The soft and mushy texture of sticky rice
# 然后再配上这个虾
in combination with the shrimps
# 鲜花虾 樱花虾
the sakura shrimps
# 樱花虾的这种鲜香
the flavor of the sakura shrimps
# 这种口感搭配
The combined texture
# 绝了 就跟阿宝这个人一样 绝了
Fantastic! Just like A Bao himself. Fantastic!
# 有模有样有味
Presentation and flavor
# 谢谢 谢谢
Thank you! Thank you!
# 他这个炒饭的技巧很到位
He has some excellent rice frying skills
# 妙 妙在哪呢？
What's the best part of it?
# 你看他这米
See, the rice
# 用水去煮
It was boiled in water
# 煮完了丝毫没有水气味
and there's absolutely no watery taste after boiling
# 这点是他炒饭最高明之处
That's the best part of his rice frying skills
# 谢谢 谢谢
Thank you! Thank you!
# 咱们炒都是干炒 干做
We cook fried rice in a dry way
# 这炒饭用糯米去炒
He used sticky rice for the fried rice
# 另一种不同的风味
which gives a different kind of flavor
# 口味非常好
and great texture
# 好 感谢阿宝
Alright. Thank you, A Bao!
# 说了半天就一个字 还是这个好
So we've said so much, just to say it's terrific!
# 我是大爷
I am Da Ye
# 我是二伯
I am Er Bai
# 我是三叔
I am San Shu
# 我们是老饭骨
We are Lao Fan Gu
# 欢迎大家订阅我们老饭骨 YouTube 频道
Please subscribe to our YouTube Channel
# 我们老饭骨组合就是教大家做菜
We are here to teach you how to cook
# 传授一些精湛的小厨艺
And to share with you some little tips
# 希望大家喜欢
Hope you like them
# 希望全球的美食爱好者喜欢我们
We that hope everyone around the world likes our videos
# 订阅我们的频道
Subscribe to our channel
# 点亮我们的小铃铛
Click the notification bell
# 同时在这里我们祝全球华人
Here, we wish everyone
# 万事如意 恭喜发财
A lot of happiness and fortune in the coming new year!